Robert L. Anderson II

Washington D.C. Metropolitan Area

240.462.5173 - RobertLAndersonJunior@gmail.com – sasrza.github.io

EXECUTIVE PROFILE

Robert brings twenty-four years of experience as a SAS Technical Consultant specializing in business intelligence, including seventeen years as Senior Technical Consulting Business Manager. He has driven customer implementations in a multitude of industries, including professional sports, government, education, healthcare, retail and manufacturing. Robert has a depth of knowledge in business intelligence platforms and a wealth of experience in advanced analytics, data preparation and custom web application development. Robert's team-first management style allows him to lead organizations, as well as be a productive team member implementing others' visions.

SAMPLING OF ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Extensive knowledge of business intelligence platforms including SAS, Tableau, R, Cognos and Qlik
- Data preparation experience with various tools including SAS, SQL Server, Oracle and Hadoop
- Implementation experience with digital marketing Customer Response Management (CRM) solutions
- Initiation, staffing and delivery of implementation services contracts
- Management and career development of an 11-member team of consultants
- Authoring of best practices for project delivery and technical functionality
- Creation of packaged services collateral

CORE COMPETENCIES

- Presales and implementation experience with a variety of business sectors, including financial services, healthcare, manufacturing, retail, K-12/highest education and state/local federal government.
- Extensive contributions to the presales effort of a multiyear contract for software and services for an international monetary organization.
- Running the day to day operations of a large consulting department with a dozen direct reports and a \$3M annual services target.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Technical Consulting Manager - January 2008 to Present

SAS Institute, Inc. - Rockville, MD - Global Hosting and US Professional Services - Business Intelligence Practice

- Specializes in Visual Analytics, Business Intelligence and custom web application development
- Manages 15-member project implementation team responsible for \$3.5M in annual services revenue
- Delivers technical implementations and assessments with a focus on Business Intelligence
- Assigns and allocates resources for technological implementations
- Responsible for training plans, mentoring and career development of Jr. Consultants
- Works closely with sales management to position strategic services opportunities
- Creates packaged fixed price and standard time & materials service offerings for presales
- Responsible for balancing internal resource utilization with 3rd party partner assignments
- Manages internal blogs and technical resource repositories to ensure knowledge sharing
- Reviews and crafts responses to presales services proposals
- Interviews and qualifies 3rd party consultants for use on projects
- Assists with on-campus interviews and associated recruitment activities

Technical Consultant Manager and Supervisor - December 2002 – December 2007

SAS Institute, Inc. – Rockville, MD – PSD - State and Local Government Operations

- Ran day-to-day operations of state and local government delivery team with a \$7.5M annual services target
- Created off the shelf service packaged offerings for presales teams
- Worked closely with sales management to position strategic services implementations
- Responsible for recruiting, interviewing, hiring and onboarding new consultants
- Collaborated with vertical teams to develop best practices for project implementations

Systems Engineer - January 2000 – November 2002

SAS Institute, Inc. – Rockville, MD – Sales and Marketing Public Sector Group

- Responsible for programming, testing, documentation, and related tasks for technology pilot implementations
- Conducted technological assessments and drafted statements of work for pilot implementations
- Served as technical lead, determining technical specifications, resource allocation and client interaction
- · Assisted sales representatives with technical insight on site visits to help influence software sales
- Conferred with management as needed to develop best practices for project delivery

Applications Developer - January 1996 – December 1999

SAS Institute Inc. - Rockville, MD - Integrated Solutions Group

- Responsible for coding modules of customized SAS Applications for client solutions
- Formulated test plans and performed Quality Assurance (QA) testing for custom software applications
- Documented the requirements gathering, design, development, and quality assurance (QA) phases
- Assisted with development of project requirements and design
- · Regularly interacted with clients to provide feedback and support during development phases

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science - North Carolina Agricultural & Technical State University - December 1995